They say money makes the world go round. But sex was invented before money.
The Two Jakes is a crime, drama, mystery film directed by Jack Nicholson.
Real estate developer Jake Berman hires private investigator and war
veteran Jake Gittes for some run-of-the-mill matrimonial work.
After Berman shoots his wife's lover, who happens to be his business partner, Gittes is drawn
into a web of conspiracy and deceit involving the oil reserves beneath Los Angeles.
While investigating, Gittes hears a voice from his past that
causes him to revisit a traumatic case in Chinatown.
J.J. "Jake" Gittes, played by Jack Nicholson.
Julius "Jake" Berman, played by Harvey Keitel.
Kitty Berman, played by Meg Tilly.
Lillian Bodine, played by Madeleine Stowe.
Cotton Weinberger, played by Eli Wallach.
Mickey Nice, played by Rubén Blades.
The Two Jakes is a 1990 American neo-noir mystery film
and the sequel to the 1974 film Chinatown.
Directed by and starring Jack Nicholson, who reprises his role of J.J.
“Jake” Gittes from the first film, the cast also features Harvey Keitel, Meg Tilly, Madeleine Stowe,
Richard Farnsworth, Frederic Forrest, David Keith, Rubén Blades, Tracey Walter and Eli Wallach.
Also reprising their roles from Chinatown are Joe Mantell, Perry Lopez,
James Hong, and, in a brief voice-over, Faye Dunaway.
The musical score for the film is by Van Dyke Parks, who
also appears as a prosecuting attorney.
Set a decade after the first film, The Two Jakes follows private investigator Gittes as he becomes
embroiled in a web of corruption, adultery, and murder involving a client, also named Jake.
The deeper he goes, the more he realizes the events may be related to
the events surrounding Evelyn Mulwray ten years prior.
The Two Jakes faced a troubled production and went
through several years of development hell.
Various actors were attached at several points, including Joe Pesci and Roy Scheider, with screenwriter
Robert Towne also at one point set to direct and producer Robert Evans set to co-star.
Filming finally took place with Nicholson at the helm, filming
around Los Angeles in the early summer of 1989.
The film was released by Paramount Pictures on August 10, 1990.
It received mixed reviews and was not a box office success, and plans for a
third film, with Gittes near the end of his life, were abandoned.
The film explores themes of los angeles,
california, private detective, neo-noir.
The tone is mind_bending and dark and emotional.